Raúl Méndez

Technology, Innovation & Development enthusiast

Engineer and psychologist driven to promote tech as a mean of human and industry development. Skilled in techniques of research, project development, psychometrics and data analysis. Willing to learn and grow.

31/2 yrs of work experience



Guadalajara, Jalisco

raul@raulmendez.me

.....

+52 3310517191

github/RaulMendezA

linkedin.com/in/RaulMendezA in

www.raulmendez.me

Experience

Telemosa Multinational Telecommunications company

HR Manager & Innovation Consultant

07/2016 - 11/2016

Coordinated the HR department, training, recruitment, contracts, payroll, regulations and innovation projects. Authority on decision making, directly answering the CEO. Achieved company's growth by scouting/interviewing 50 candidates/mo, as well as innovating in processes, services and brand identity.

DEMOLA Finnish Innovation Network

Innovation Consultant Part-time external project/consultancy

05/2016 - 11/2016

Consultancy on innovation and project dev among DEMOLA's 4th generation teams in America. Created and justified workshops and materials to aid the research and solution design on each team's problematic and their resulting papers reviewing.

Innovation Project Lead

08/2015 - 05/2016

- Uroboros Project Alquimia Leading marketing, communication and consulting company
 Proposed an all-new Innovation Department based on a multi-disciplinary team for achieving and managing R&D on their client's accounts.
- SkillzzUp Project SkillzzUp Real-time assessment software company in Finland Proposed a log and feedback platform of an individual's academic and professional skills and achievements. Validated on Neurology and Education theory. It was successfully acquired by our partner in Finland (#1 education system by PISA), piloted in education fairs around the world and universities in China, USA, UAE along with the Finnish Embassy.

Leinster Animal Rescue (Dublin, Ireland) Irish animal sheltering organization

HR Generalist & Innovation Consultant

Summer 2015

Recruitment, innovation and project management. Achieved company's growth by obtaining new personnel as well as funds through many projects. First experience working abroad, being constantly appreciated for my domain on the language.

ISSSTE Main health care institution of the Mexican federal system

HR Generalist

01/2014 - 12/2014

Developed skills on recruitment and interviewing new staff, bureaucracy streamlining and personnel description updating. Formally required new personnel, acquiring 4 new federal positions/Medics.

FM4 Research and pro-human rights organization

Research Assistant

01/2013 - 12/2013

Planned and executed a year-long qualitative / quantitative research project on transmigration. The 200-page paper had a strong impact on the local and massive media notion; institutions like Amnesty International used it in their own work on the matter, also becoming my first scientific community publication.

Education

2017 - 2021

Bachelor's degree - Computer Systems Engineering On course

Western Institute of Technology and Higher Education (ITESO)

Relevant Subjects

Algorithmic Strategy | Software Design | Applications and Web Development | Databases for Decision Making | Computational Architecture

2011 - 2016

Bachelor's degree - Psychology Graduate

Western Institute of Technology and Higher Education (ITESO)

Relevant Subjects

Neurology | Statistics | Human Resources | Innovation & Technology Management | Research Methodology | Psychoanalysis

12/2014 - 08/2015 Ireland

Exchange Program in Ireland - Cognitive Science

Waterford Institute of Technology (WIT)

Relevant Subjects

Cognition & Perception | Social Psychology | Abnormal Psychology

Skills & Competences

Project development:

Skilled in project and business ideas development, **Scrum**, Lean/agile methodologies, research through APA and **IEEE** documentation, teamwork, critical + creative thinking, listening and **attention to detail**.

- -MisProfesores: teacher evaluation/review platform on both an Android app (Kotlin, Java, Parse) and website (JavaScript, MongoDB, HTML). Front-end and interfaces logic.
- -PharmaFine: e-commerce website (Angular) for a nutrition supplement business project. Currently on dev, Front and back-end.
- -SkillzUp: adaptation to our education system along with ITESO. Developed an **MVP and workshops** to test it.

Others include **clustering** Spotify datasets to contrast the clusters to its pre-assigned genres and **connecting** food delivery businesses and car-washing services within a small city with the **end user** (business model, app **mocking and prototyping**).

Coding

Higher and lower level languages, mainly Java, C and JavaScript/ TypeScript (Angular), as well as Kotlin, Python, Assembly (MIPS, 8051), querying and database design.

Continuous Education

Quick learner. **Self-actualization** by congresses, expo's, lectures, books, symposiums, **hackathons** and **workshops** such as: *Business Model Canvas with Alexander Osterwalder, International Astronautical Congress, Campus Party, StartUp Weekend, EduExpo's, Scrum/Agile and many developers, science and tech crash courses.*

Languages

Spanish English French

Native Expert Beginner TOEFL just started

Interests

Software Design | Web Design | Design | STEM |
Beer | Business | Research | Social Psychology |
Journalism | Neuroscience | Genre Studies |
Education | AI | UX & UI